Guide to the Condit W. Cutler Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Condit W. Cutler Papers,
1918-ca.1952.
Cutler, Condict W. (Condict Walker), 1888-1958.
2 linear ft. ( ca. 100 items in 3 boxes).
Columbia University, Rare Book and Manuscripts Library, Butler Library, 535 West 114th Street, New York, N.Y. 10027.
4079686
Biographical Note
Dr. Cutler was a specialist in surgery and diseases of the hand. He was born in Morristown, N.J., August 9, 1888. After graduating from Columbia College in 1910 and the Columbia School of Medicine in 1912, he interned at Roosevelt Hospital where he was staff surgeon and consulting surgeon until his death. Dr. Cutler served in both World Wars and was associated with Columbia in many capacities. He was Instructor in Surgery from 1919-1929, an Alumni Trustee from 1939-1944, Professor of Clinical Surgery 1947-1954, a past president of the Columbia College Alumni Association and a past Commander of the University's American Legion Post. Dr. Cutler authored The Hand: Its Diseases and Disabilities in 1941, a typescript of which is in the collection.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of about 50 letters, chiefly from Dr. Cutler's Columbia associates, his diary of World War I period (January-April 1918), 17 diplomas and honors, clippings, pamphlets, photographs as well as his academic hood and his many honorary medals.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 2 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Material
Subjects
United States.--Army--Foreign service--France.; United States.--Army--Surgeons.; Surgeons--United States.; Hand--Surgery.; World War, 1914-1918--France.; World War, 1914-1918--Medical care.; Medicine, Military--United States.; Autobiographies.; Biographies.; Diaries.; Diplomas.; Scrapbooks.; Memorabilia.; Photoprints.; Awards.; Surgeons--United States.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-5. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
09/19/59 M-59-09-19 Freeman, Leon S. Mrs. Gift
Gift of Mrs. Leon S. Freeman, 1959.
- Series I: Cataloged Material
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence
    - Beckman, H.C. "Chief" To Condict W. Cutler, Jr., Westport, NY, 25 Aug 1948, (1 page t.l.s., ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. To H.C. Beckman, [France?], 12 March 1918, (4 pages a.l.s., ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. To H.C. Beckman, France, 14 May 1918, (2 pages t.l.s., ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. To H.C. Beckman, France, 3 June 1918, (4 pages a.l.s., ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. To H.C. Beckman, France, 30 June 1918, (4 pages a.l.s., ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. To H.C. Beckman, France, 30 July 1918, (6 pages a.l.s., ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. To H.C. Beckman, [France], 22 Aug 1918, (8 pages a.l.s., ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. To Lou, [France], 8 Sept 1918, (2 pages t.l.s. (carbon), ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. Letters to Dr. Cutler relating to his resignation as Attending Surgeon at Roosevelt Hospital, 1952, (5 pieces, ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. Letters of congratulation upon his election as Trustee of Columbia University from: Marcus Hartley Dodge (2), Nicholas Murray Butler, Thomas S. McLane, Edmund A. Prentis, Frank R. Whelan, Willard C. Rappleye, Marston T. Bogert, Dwight D. Eisenhower (telegram), Frederick Coykendall (telegram), Nicholas Murray Butler (telegram, Clarence E. Lovejoy, (12 pieces, ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. Miscellaneous correspondence, (5 pieces, ) (Box 1)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D. To Condict W. Cutler, Jr., Supreme Headquarters, Allied Powers Europe, 26 March 1952, (1 page t.l.s., ) (Box 1)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D. To Condict W. Cutler, Jr., Denver, 23 July 1952, (1 page t.l.s., ) (Box 1)
    - Ford, Ernest M. To Condict W. Cutler, Jr., New York, 26 June 1950, (1 page t.l.s., ) (Box 1)
    - LaGuardia, Fiorello To Condict W. Cutler, Jr., New York, 9 Nov 1940, (1 page t.l.s., ) (Box 1)
    - State of New Jersey. Board of Medical Examiners To Condict W. Cutler, Jr., Trenton, NJ, 20 May 1952, (1 Doc. License to practice, ) (Box 1)
    - Thompson, T. Campbell To Condict W. Cutler, Jr., New York, 11 Aug 1942, (2 pages t.l.s., ) (Box 1)
    - Young Men's Christian Association To Condict W. Cutler, Jr., [New York?], 1951, (1 doc. Centennial citation, ) (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.2: Manuscripts
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. Surgery of the Hand, (134 pages t.ms. (carbon), ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. Bibliography, (3 pages, ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. Letters to Dr. Cutler relating to his service with the Department of Hospitals of the City of New York, 1939-1953, (3 pieces, ) (Box 1)
    - Cutler, Condict W., Jr. Personal and professional record, (3 pages, ) (Box 1)
- Series II: Arranged Material
  - Memorabilia (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Diplomas (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook (Box 5)